Dangerous Knowledge
(2007.8.8 BBC Four)
딕테이션, 한/영 자막 제작
DCinside 과학갤/다큐갤 '디핑'
croydon.egloos.com
자연을 지배하는 것은
과학의 법칙입니다
Beneath the surface of the world are the rules of science.
그리고 그 아래에는 더욱
심오한 규칙들이 숨어 있습니다
But beneath them, there is a far deeper set of rules.
과학 법칙의 본질을 설명하며
인간이 과학을 이해할 수 있게 돕는
A matrix of pure mathematics which explains the nature of the rules of science
수학 체계가 바로 그것입니다
and how it is we can understand them in the first place.
한 알의 모래 속에서 세계를 보고
한 송이 들꽃에서 천국을 보기 위해
To see a world in a grain of sand
And a heaven in a wild flower,
그대 손바닥 안에 무한을 붙들고
순간 속에 영원을 담아라
(from '순수의 전조' - 윌리엄 블레이크)
Hold infinity in the palm of your hand
And eternity in an hour
신이 없다면, 이제
어떤 사상에 의지해야 할까요?
What is the system that everything has to adhere to, if there is no God?
특별히 주의를 기울이지 않으면
언제든 나를 잡아먹어버릴..
You had these ideas and.. you had to be very careful because any moment they would bite you.
멋져 보이지만
매우 위험한 생각입니다
They sounded great but they were very dangerous.
하지만 두려운 면도 있습니다.
주저하며 뒤로 물러서게 되죠
But then of course people get scared, so they pull back from the edge of the precipice.
그런데 이것은
좋다 싫다의 문제가 아닙니다
Well, this is not a matter of liking it or not. It is..
증명이 되었고,
받아들여야만 하는 것이죠
you have here this proof and.. one has to live with it.
이것은 익숙하게 여겨왔던
수학과 자연의 확실성을 와해시킨
This film is about how a small group of the most brilliant minds
소수의 뛰어난 학자들의
업적에 대한 이야기입니다
unravelled our old cozy certainties about math and the universe.
또한, 이 문제에 사로잡혀
정신이상이나 자살에 이를 지경까지
It is also about how once they had looked at these problems they could not look away,
매달렸던 그들의 삶에 관한
이야기이기도 합니다
and pursued the questions to the brink of insanity and then over it to madness and suicide.
비극적인 삶이었으나,
그들이 밝혀낸것은 엄연한 진리입니다
But for all their tragedies, what they saw is still true.
그들의 업적은 당대에
격렬한 반대에 부딪쳤으며
Their contemporaries largely rejected the significance of their work,
오늘날의 우리도
완전히 계승하지 못했습니다
and we have yet to fully inherit it.
아직 그들이 조망한 새로운 세계의
입구에 서 있을 뿐입니다
Today, we still stand only on the threshold of the world they saw.
위험한 지식
저는 데이빗 멀론입니다
My name is David Malone.
잘 알려져 있지 않지만
우리 시대에 커다란 영향을 끼친
And this is my homage to four great thinkers, who without most of us even having heard of them,
4명의 위대한 지성,
그리고 오늘날 시사하는 바가 큰
have profoundly influenced the nature of our age.
그들에 관한 이야기를
들려드리고자 합니다
and whose stories have, I think, an important message for us today.
독일 동부의 작은 도시
할레입니다
This is Halle, a provincial town in eastern Germany
마틴 루터가 한때 여기서
종교개혁을 설파하기도 했죠
where Martin Luther once preached the Reformation.
이야기의 시작은
이곳 대학의 수학 교수였던
Our story starts here at the town's university with the mathematics professor,
게오르그 칸토어입니다.
그는 비록 의도한건 아니지만
a man called Georg Cantor who started a revolution he never really meant to start
결국 수학과 과학의 토대를 뒤흔든
대혁명의 시발점이 되었습니다
but which eventually threatened to shake the whole of mathematics and science on its foundations.
그것은 간단한 질문에서 시작되었죠
And he started his revolution by asking himself a simple question.
"도대체 무한은 얼마나 큰 것인가?"
"How big is infinity?"
- 신(神)의 전령 -
칸토어는 정말 굉장하죠
Cantor is wonderful because it's so crazy.
제정신이 아닐만큼
대단한 상상력의 소유자입니다
It's the equivalent of being on drugs.
It's just an incredible feat of imagination.
게오르그 칸토어는 세계 최고의
수학자 중 한 명입니다
Georg Cantor is one of the greatest mathematicians of the world.
고대 그리스 이래 많은 수학자들이
같은 의문을 품었습니다
Others before him, going back to the ancient Greeks at least, had asked the question.
누구도 감히 맞서지 못했던
이 문제와 씨름하여
But it was Cantor who made the journey no one else ever had and found the answer.
답을 찾은 것은 칸토어였습니다
그러나 그 대가를 치러야했죠
But he paid a price for his discovery.
이것이 유일하게 남아있는
칸토어의 흉상입니다
This is the only bust there is of Georg Cantor.
그가 세상을 뜨기
1년 전에 만들어졌죠
It was made just one year before he died.
그는 정신병원에서
홀로 죽음을 맞았습니다
And he died utterly alone in an insane asylum.
당대 최고 수학자의 정신을 병들게 한
원인은 무엇이었을까요?
The question is: what could the greatest mathematician of his century
have seen that could drive him insane?
칸토어가 골몰한 주제는 단순히
수학의 문제에 불과한 것이 아니었습니다
If all that Cantor had seen was mathematics, then his story would be of limited interest.
이것이 가지는 커다란 중요성을
그도 처음부터 알고 있었습니다
But from the beginning, Cantor realized his work had far wider significance.
그는 이를 통해 인간의 지성이
진리와 확실성을 획득할거라 기대했지만
He believed it could take the human mind towards greater, transcendent truth and certainty.
결국 자신의 연구가 그 확실성을
더욱 더 멀어지게 만들고
What he never suspected was that eventually his math
would make that certainty ever more elusive,
결코 닿을수 없는 신기루로
만들어버릴 것임은 알지 못했습니다
perhaps even destroy the possibility of ever reaching it.
칸토어는 종교적인 사람이었습니다
If you want to understand Georg Cantor
you have to understand he was a religious man, though not in a conventional sense.
그러나 일반적인 종교와는 달랐죠
그는 아마도
이 교회에 온 적은 있지만
He almost certainly came to this church
저기 보이는 신을 믿지는 않았습니다
but that's not his God.
그는 구원과 부활을 말하는
신에는 관심이 없었습니다
He wasn't interested in the God whose mysteries were redemption and resurrection.
그에게는 어릴적부터 들려오던
목소리가 있었습니다
Ever since he was just a boy he had heard what he called
그의 표현을 빌면 '나를 수학으로
인도하는 비밀의 목소리' 였죠
'a secret voice calling him to mathematics'.
일평생 그를 따라다닌 목소리,
이것이 칸토어의 신이었습니다
That voice which he heard all his life, in his mind, was God.
칸토어에겐 무한을 다루는
그의 수학은 옳아야만 했습니다
So for Cantor, his mathematics of infinity had to be correct.
진정 무한한 존재인
신이 내려준 계시이기 때문이죠
Because God, the true infinite, had revealed it to him.
지금은 알지 못하는 것들이
모습을 드러낼 때가 오게 되리니..
These things which are now hidden from you will be brought into the light..
집합론에 관한 1895년 마지막 논문은
세 줄의 경구로 시작합니다
If you look at Cantor's last major publication about set theory in 1895, it starts with three aphorisms.
그중 세번째는 성경의
고린도전서에서 따온 것인데
and his third motto is from the bible and it's from Corinthians.
조셉 도벤 - 과학사가, 뉴욕시립대학
지금은 알지 못하는 것들이 결국
모습을 드러낼 것이다.. 그런 내용이죠
And it's "that which has been hidden to you will eventually be brought into the light."
칸토어는 정말로 자기가 신의 전령이며,
미지의 대상이던 무한에 관한 이론을
And Cantor, I think, really believed he was the messenger,
that this theory that had been hidden, he was God's means
이 세상으로 불러내는 사명을 띠고 있다고
믿었던 것 같습니다
of bringing this theory of the infinite to the world.
카린 리히터 - 수학자, 할레 대학
칸토어의 종교적 입장과 수학은
모순되는 것이 아닙니다
There is no contradiction for Cantor between his religious thinking and his mathematics.
그는 자신의 수학적 영감을
신이 주신 선물로 이해했습니다
He understood or he was thinking that his ideas were a gift of God.
그레고리 채이틴 - 수학자, IBM 연구소
저는 칸토어가 신을 이해하려고
노력한 것이라고 봅니다
My view was that Cantor was trying to understand God,
그레고리 채이틴 - 수학자, IBM 연구소
'수학 신학'.. 쯤 될까요?
그런 방향이었다고 생각합니다
and that this was really like a 'mathematical theology' that he was doing.
칸토어가 믿은 신은 조물주 신이며,
따라서 그의 진리는
Cantor's God was the creator God, the God who set the planets spinning in their orbits
만물의 운동을 지배하는
영원하고 완벽한 운동 법칙입니다
whose mysteries were the eternal and perfect laws of motion.
이 운동 법칙을 이해함으로써 우리는
Laws whose discovery had launched the modern world
자연을 곡선, 운동 궤적, 힘 같은
관점으로 바라보게 되었으며
and allowed us to see the world as curves, trajectories and forces
현대에는 마침내
달까지 여행할 수 있었습니다
and which would one day even put men on the moon.
신이 창조하고 뉴턴과 라이프니츠*가 발견한
영원불멸한 확실성의 세계입니다
* 현대적인 미적분학의 창시자들
The eternal certainties laid down by God which Newton and Leibniz had discovered.
그런데 그 핵심에는
'무한'이라는 골칫거리가 있습니다
And it was infinity which lay at the heart of it all.
But there was a problem with it.
운동궤적의 매끈한 곡선은,
사실 뜯어보면 매끈하지 않습니다
If you look at that beautiful smooth curve of motion, you notice it's not actually smooth.
무한히 짧은 선분들이
무한히 많이 모인 것입니다
It's made of an infinite number of infinitesimally small straight lines.
각각의 선분은
정지된 순간에 해당하죠
And each line is an instant in which nothing moves.
이것들을 영화 필름처럼 늘어놓으면
원래의 운동 궤적이 얻어집니다
But like frames of film, if you run one after another you get motion. And it works.
분명히 무한의 개념이 들어있지만,
어쨌든 잘 들어맞습니다
The whole thing relies on infinity, but it works.
그래서, 이해하기 힘든 무한이란 개념은
다들 모른척 피했습니다
Because it worked, everyone said, "All right, we don't understand infinity. Just leave it alone."
그러나 칸토어는 이 무한이라는
핵심을 꼭 이해해야 한다고 생각했습니다
Cantor comes along and says, "No, if this whole thing rests on infinity we have to understand it."
칸토어는 종교적인 인간이었죠
Now remember Cantor was a religious man.
따라서 그에겐 저 수학 기호(∞ 무한대)가
종교적 진리이기도 한 것입니다
So for him, that symbol isn't just a scientific mystery. It's a religious mystery as well.
신은 수학을 이용하여
만물의 운행을 관장합니다
Here's the math that God uses to keep creation in motion.
바로 그 수학의 핵심에
무한의 신비가 숨어있죠
And at its heart lies the deeper mystery of infinity.
그러나 무한의 신비를 터득하려는
노력은 모두 실패하였습니다
But it was a mystery that had so far defied every mind that had looked at it.
근대에 최초로 도전장을
던진 것은 갈릴레오였습니다
The first modern thinker to confront the infinite was Galileo.
그의 접근법은 원을 이용한 것입니다
And he tried to do it using the circle.
이런것입니다
This is how he did it.
여기 원을 그립니다
First of all, draw a circle.
이 원에 내접하는 삼각형,
또 사각형, 오각형,..을 그립니다
Now put a triangle inside it, then a square. Keep on going, keep adding sides.
뭔가 보이시나요?
Eventually you realize what the circle is.
원은 바로 무한히 짧은 변들이
무한히 많이 모인 다각형이로군요
It's a shape with infinitely many, infinitesimally small sides,
신기하죠?
단순한 원에도 무한이 들어있습니다
which seems great. Now you hold the infinite and the infinitesimal in your hands.
그런데 이 관찰은
괴이한 모순을 낳습니다
But as soon as he'd done that, he realized he'd actually opened up a horrible illogical paradox.
바깥에 좀더 큰 원을 그려 볼까요
Because he said, let's draw a bigger circle outside.
이제 지극히 날카로운 연필로,
원의 중심으로부터..
And now with an infinitely sharp pencil, draw from the center,
안쪽 원을 이루는 (무한히 짧은) 선분들
각각에 이르는 가느다란 직선들을 긋습니다
infinitely sharp lines, one for each of the lines of the inner circle.
지금 그은 직선들은 무한히 많습니다.
그럼 안쪽 원을 가득 채우겠죠?
All right, there's infinite number of them. They should be enough for the inner circle.
이제 이 직선들을 바깥쪽 원까지 연장합니다.
각각의 선들은 점점 벌어지죠?
Now extend those lines out to meet the outer circle.
Those lines are diverging,
그럼 바깥쪽 원에 다다랐을 때는
이 직선들 사이에 '틈'이 생기게 됩니다
which means when you get to the outer circle, if you look really carefully there would be gaps.
바깥쪽 원을 채우기엔
부족하다는 얘기죠!
They won't be enough!
갈릴레오 曰, "말도 안된다.
무한히 많은 직선들로도 부족하다니?"
And Galileo just said, "That makes no sense. If there is an infinite number it should be enough!"
결국 그는, 신(神)이라면 몰라도..
at which point he said we just can't understand the infinite.
유한한 존재인 인간은
무한을 이해할수 없다고 결론내렸습니다
Maybe God can, but with our finite minds we can't.
무한 개념이 꼭 필요하면 쓰되,
그걸 이해하려고 들지는 말자는 거죠
So, let's use the concept if we must.
But let's not try and understand infinity.
바로 이러한 경향이
칸토어 전까지 이어졌습니다
And that's exactly how they left it until Georg Cantor came along.
신(神)은 칸토어의 편에
서 있는듯 했습니다
At first it must have seemed to Cantor that God really was on his side.
불과 몇년 동안, 그는
결혼하고 가정을 꾸리고
In the space of only a few years he married, began a family
무한에 관한 혁명적인
첫번째 논문을 발표합니다
and published his first groundbreaking paper about Infinity.
무한은 그저 끝없이 큰 수라고
막연하게만 여겨 왔지만
Where previously infinity had just been a vague number without end
칸토어는 전혀 새로운 경지를
개척했습니다
Cantor saw a whole new world opening up.
칸토어의 참신한 발상은,
"숫자 1에 1을 더할 수 있는데.."
Cantor did a new step and he said, "I want to add one plus one."
".. 무한에 무한을 더하지 못할
이유가 무엇인가? .."
And Cantor said, "Okay, why not I can add infinity plus infinity? .."
"..그것도 가능할거야."
이게 그 이론의 출발점이었습니다
".. That's also possible." And this was the starting point of his theory.
그는 무한을 더하고 뺄 수
있다는것 뿐만 아니라
Cantor found he could add and subtract infinities, and in fact
무한을 대상으로 하는
전혀 새로운 수학을 발견했습니다
discovered there was a vast new mathematics of the infinite.
'그래, 대충 이런게 무한이지'
하고 넘어갔던 무한이란 것이
You really finally feel for the first time that the infinite is no longer
더이상 애매모호한 개념이 아님을
처음으로 깨달았습니다
this amorphous concept - "Well it's infinite, and that's all you can say about it."
칸토어는 무한을 명확하고 엄밀한
대상으로 다루는 방법을 알아냈습니다
But Cantor says no, there's a way you can make this very precise and I can make it very definite as well.
1872년까지 칸토어는
영감에 넘쳤습니다
By 1872, Cantor is a man inspired.
그 누구도 알지 못했던
무한의 실체도 이미 파악했죠
He's already grasped and understood the nature of real infinity which no one before him had done.
같은 해, 이곳 알프스에서
But in that same year he comes up here to the Alps
칸토어는 그의 이론을 이해하는
유일한 사람을 만났습니다
to meet the only other man who really understood his work,
수학자 리처드 데데킨트였죠
a mathematician called Richard Dedekind.
이때가 그의 삶에서 가장 행복하고
지적으로 왕성하던 시절이었을겁니다
And this time is probably the happiest and most inspired period of Cantor's life.
그 만남 후 1년만에
그는 놀라운 발견을 해냅니다
Within a year of their meeting he announces an astonishing discovery
무한보다 더 큰 무한이 있으며,
that beyond infinity there's another larger infinity
심지어 수많은 무한들의 세계에
등급까지 있다는 사실입니다
and possibly even a whole hierarchy of different infinities.
직관적으로는 이상해 보이겠지만,
Though it is contrary to every intuition,
칸토어는 무한에도
크고 작음이 있음을 간파했습니다
Cantor began to see that some infinities are bigger than others.
수직선(數直線) 위에는 무한히 많은
정수와 유리수들이 놓여 있습니다
He already knew that when you looked at the number line
it divided up into an infinite number of whole numbers and fractions.
그런데 잘 살펴보면,
이들의 개수는 무한히 많은데도
But Cantor found that as he looked closer at this line,
that infinite though the fractions are,
가까운 두 유리수 사이에도
또다른 수들이 바글바글합니다
each one is separated from the next by a wilderness of other numbers.
그것은 π 같은 무리수들로,
Irrational numbers like π,
값을 표기하는데만도
무한히 많은 자릿수가 필요합니다
which require an infinite number of decimal places just to define them.
놀랍게도 이 무리수들의 개수(무한)는
유리수들의 개수(역시 무한)보다..
Against all logic, the infinity of these numbers was unmeasurably, uncountably larger than the first.
..비교도 안될만큼
더 많다는 것이 밝혀졌습니다
'무한보다 더 큰 무한'의 존재를
칸토어가 증명한 것입니다
What had frightened Galileo, Cantor had proved.
There was a larger infinity.
칸토어의 천재성은 오늘날까지도
수학자들을 고무시킵니다
Today, Cantor's genius continues to inspire the work of some of the greatest mathematicians.
그레고리 채이틴도
그러한 석학 중 한명이죠
Greg Chaitin is recognized as one of the most brilliant.
무한은 늘 존재했지만
수학자들은 이것을 가둬놓았어요
Well infinity was always there but they tried to contain it, they tried to keep it in a cage.
'실제 무한'*이니 '잠재 무한'*이니
하는 식으로 논하고 등등..
* 실제로 무한한 값과, 유한한 값이지만
한없이 커질 수 있는 값을 구분하던 용어
And people would talk about potential infinity not as opposed to actual infinity.
반면에 칸토어는
용감하게 나아갔습니다
But Cantor just goes all the way. He just goes totally berserk.
그리하여 발견한 것이, 무한 위에
그것보다 더 큰 무한, 더 큰 무한..
And then you find that you have infinities and bigger infinities and even bigger infinities
심지어 무한히 많은 무한들을 늘어놓아도
이들 전부보다 더 큰 무한이 또 있고..
and for any infinite series of infinities, there are infinities that go bigger than all of them.
이렇게 큰 값들을 어떻게 이름 붙이고
구분하겠나 싶죠?
And you get numbers so big that you wonder how you could even name them.
이름을 다 붙일수도 없습니다
Infinities are so big that you can't even give them names.
아무튼 환상적인 얘기죠
This is just fantastic stuff.
다시 말해 이런 것이었죠,
"어떤 개념이든 가져오면 더 큰걸 만들어주마!"
So in a way what he's saying is: "Given any set of concepts, I'm going to invent something that's bigger!"
궤변처럼 보일만도 합니다
So this is paradoxical essentially.
그래서 애초부터 무한을 논하는것은
대단히 어려운 문제입니다
So there's something inherently ungraspable that escapes you from this conception.
칸토어가 엄청난 일을 한거죠
So it's absolutely breathtaking, it's great stuff.
이것이 미분방정식, 건축, 항공공학
같은것과 관계 없을지라도.. 뭐 어때요?
Now it may not have anything to do with partial differential equations,
building bridges, designing air foils. But who cares?
칸토어의 대담한 생각은 새로운 지평을 열고
수학을 영원히 바꿔놓았습니다
The sheer audacity of Cantor's ideas had thrown open the doors and changed mathematics forever.
그 자신도 그걸 알았죠
And he knew it.
칸토어의 기분은 어땠을까요?
We can't know exactly how he felt.
채이틴도 이런 심오한 발견의
순간을 경험했습니다
But Greg Chaitin has also felt those rare moments of profound insight.
울창한 숲 속을 걷습니다
Here we are down in the forest, and..
사방이 나무로 빽빽해서
길을 알아보기도 어렵죠
we can't see very far in any direction.
힘들고 지쳤지만 그래도
열심히 걸어갑니다
And you struggle up knowing the fact that you are tired and weary.
겨우겨우 산을 오르며 둘러보면
아름다운 경치가 드러납니다
You struggle up a mountain, and the higher you go the more beautiful and breathtaking the views are.
운이 따르면
산 정상에도 오를 수 있죠
And then, if you're lucky you get to the top of the mountain.
이것은 어떤 초월적인 경험입니다
That can be a transcendental experience.
종교적인 사람이라면
신에게 다가간 느낌이라고 할만한..
A spiritual person would say they feel closer to God.
그럼 갑자기 모든 방향으로
전망이 확 트이겠죠
You have this breathtaking view. All of a sudden you can see in all directions and things make sense.
모든것이 완전히 이해됩니다
이전에 알지 못하던 것을
이해하는 것은 아름다운 일입니다
It's beautiful to understand something that you couldn't understand before.
그런데 바로 그 순간,
더 많은 새로운 문제들이 생겨납니다
The problem is, the moment you understand one thing that raises more questions.
이 산의 정상에 오르고 나면
저 멀리 더 높은 산들이 보이는것이죠
So in other words the moment you climb one mountain then you see off in the distance,
behind the haze, much higher mountains.
칸토어의 이론은 비유하자면
산 너머 더 높은 산들이 있고
His theory is all about the fact that the mountains get higher and higher,
아무리 많은 산을 올라도, 그 모두를
능가하는 더 높은 산이 있다는 것입니다
and no range is equal enough because there are always mountain ranges
beyond any range that you can understand or conceive of.
이것은 어찌 보면 수학자들을
자유롭게 놓아주는 발견일수 있습니다
So this is tremendously liberating effect on mathematics, or ought to.
하지만 두려운 면도 있습니다.
주저하며 뒤로 물러서게 되죠
But then of course people get scared. So they pull back from the edge of the precipice.
이 발견은 칸토어를 매혹시킨 반면,
비판자들을 놀라게 했습니다
What was inspiring for Cantor frightened his critics.
그들이 생각한 수학은
명료함과 확실성을 추구하는 것입니다
They saw mathematics as the pursuit of clarity and certainty.
무리수와 무한에 관한 칸토어의 생각은
확실성을 훼손하는 것으로 보였으므로
Everything Cantor was doing, his irrational numbers and his illogical infinities
seemed to them to be eating away at certainty.
그들은 칸토어를
매우 적대시했습니다
He soon faced a deep and implacable hostility.
칸토어가 평생을 보낸 대학의
강의실입니다
This is the main lecture theater in the university where Cantor spent his entire professional life.
제 생각에 칸토어는
사면초가의 상태였을 것입니다
A life that he felt trapped in, and I think with some justification.
다른 수학자들은 칸토어가 논문을
출판하지 못하게 막으려 했습니다
Other mathematicians actually tried to prevent Cantor publishing his papers.
그는 늘 비엔나, 베를린 등의 명문대에서
자신을 불러주기를 바랬지만
Cantor always dreamed that he'd receive an invitation
to one of the great universities like Vienna or Berlin.
결코 그런 일은 없었습니다
But they were invitations which never came.
게다가 인신공격까지 당했습니다
And he was also attacked personally.
위대한 수학자
앙리 푸앙카레마저
The great mathematician Henri Poincare said
칸토어의 이론은
수학이 잠깐 앓고 있는 질병일뿐이며
that Cantor's mathematics was a sickness from which one day math would recover.
곧 치료될 것이라고 했습니다
심지어, 한때 친구이자
스승이었던 크로네커는
And worse, his one time friend and teacher Kroneker
그를 '후학들을 망쳐놓는 존재'라며
비난했습니다
said that Cantor was a corruptor of youth.
칸토어는 그의 이론과 함께
이곳에 갇혀 있었던 셈입니다
Cantor felt that he and his ideas were being caged or quarantined here
마치 병에 걸린 환자처럼요
as if they were some kind of sickness.
봉인을 풀고 보니까
위험한 도깨비가 튀어나온겁니다
The genie got out of the bottle. It was a very dangerous genie.
왜냐면 이 개념은 본질적으로
자기모순적인 측면이 있거든요
because the concepts that Cantor played with are intrinsically, inherently self-contradictory.
사람들은 그 현실을 직시하기 싫어했고,
대신 집합론을 축소시켜 버렸죠
(칸토어가 현대적 집합론을 창조했고,
무한집합에서 난점들이 발생했음)
And people don't like to face up to that. They've emasculated set theory. They have this..
'체르멜로-프랭켈 집합론'인데
안전하지만 좀 김빠진 이론입니다
this version which is safe, called Zermelo-Fraenkel set theory, which is sort of a watered-down.
그렇게 되니 재미있는 부분들도
같이 날아가버렸습니다
But you see that takes all the fun out of it.
For me, the fun of Cantor was that he was playing on the edge.
칸토어처럼 아슬아슬하게
줄타기하는 편이 재밌는데 말이죠
그러니까 어떤 것이냐면
You know the idea was you had these ideas and..
특별히 주의를 기울이지 않으면
언제든 나를 잡아먹어버릴..
you had to be very careful because at any moment they would bite you.
멋져 보이지만 매우 위험한,
자기모순에 가까운 논리들입니다
They sounded great but they were very dangerous.
You see they were almost self-contradictory.
예를 들어 '모든 것들의 집합'
같은 개념은 자기모순을 낳습니다
('러셀의 역설')
The notion of 'the set of everything' for example is self-contradictory.
모두들 기겁했죠
And people got frightened.
비판자들은, 칸토어가 수학의 생명인
확실성과 명료함을 몰아내어
His critics feared Cantor was going to dislodge the certainty and clarity vital to mathematics and logic
그것을 영영 되찾지 못할까
두려워했습니다
which might not be able to be put back.
그가 해결 불가능한 불확실성을
수학으로 끌고온 것으로 보았기 때문이죠
It seemed Cantor had opened math to the very thing that was supposed to save us from irresolvable uncertainty.
이론을 완결지어야 반대파를 설득할수
있음을 칸토어도 알고 있었습니다
Cantor knew the only way to convince his critics was to make his theory complete.
무한에 대한 총체적인 논리 체계를
세울 수 있을까요?
Could he show there was a logic to his infinities - some system that bound them altogether.
그가 반드시 밝혀내야만 할 것은
무한들 사이의 관계입니다
What he absolutely must decide now is what's the relationship between them.
성공한다면 완벽한 이론이 되지만
If he can do that, then his theory is perfect.
그렇지 못하면
불완전한 조각들에 불과합니다
If he can't, then all he has is bits.
무한들 사이의 관계에 대한 문제,
So he has to decide what's the relationship between them.
이것이 바로 '연속체 가설'입니다
And that question is the 'continuum hypothesis'.
그는 고립된 속에서도
반대를 무릅쓰고 더욱 노력했습니다
No matter how isolated he became, the more he was opposed, the more he struggled.
여느 사람이라면 포기했겠지만
그는 달랐습니다
Where another person might have given up, Cantor didn't.
임상심리학자
루이스 새스의 추측은
Clinical psychologist Dr. Louis Sass suggests
고립되길 두려워하지 않는 태도가
칸토어의 천재성을 발현시켰다는 것입니다
it is precisely this ability to be isolated which is key to Cantor's genius.
당연하게 여기던 지식에
안주하지 않고
I think that willingness to step into a realm
한발 더 나아가려는
의지가 필수적입니다
beyond taken-for-granted is absolutely essential.
루이스 새스 - 임상심리학자, 럿거스 대학
그런데 그러한 사람이라면
결국 역외자 취급을 받기 십상입니다
But I think if you are a person who takes that step
in a way you're already doomed to living outside in some way.
단순히 학문적인 이유에서만
그런 것은 아닙니다
So it's not as if it's only the intellectual project itself that takes you out there.
개인적인 성격이나 성향도
그 이유가 됩니다
There's something about you as a person, that is, just..
남들과 달리, 자연스럽지 않은 것을
자연스럽게 받아들이는 사람이니까요
that unnaturalness so to speak comes so naturally to you.
칸토어는 덫에 빠졌지만
Cantor was trapped.
그의 삶에 비추어 보면
포기는 생각도 못할 일이었습니다
There were too many things that went to the core of who he was for him to be able to give up.
그는 어릴 때 아버지로부터
받은 편지를
When Cantor was just a boy, his father sent him a letter
가장 소중한 물건으로 여겨
평생 가지고 다녔습니다
which became his most precious possession and which he carried with him all his life.
그의 성공을 바라는 온가족의 마음이
편지에 담겨 있었습니다
In it his father told him how the whole family looked to him to achieve greatness.
또한 용기를 가지고
비판과 반대를 이겨낼 것과
How he would come to nothing if he did not have the courage to overcome criticism and adversity,
신을 믿고 따르며
단념하지 말 것을 부탁했습니다
how he must trust in God to guide him and never give up.
그는 그렇게 했습니다
And he never did.
조셉 도벤 - 과학사가, 뉴욕시립대학
칸토어가 옳다고 확신했던
그 자신의 이론이
I think here you come to the root of the problem for Cantor of a theory
문제의 근원에
자리하고 있습니다
that he was certain was correct,
신의 계시이기에
옳다고 믿었던 이론이죠
in part because he believed that it had come to him as a message from God.
그 자신이 최초로 제시한 문제들을
풀지 못했던 어려움에 대처하고
There's a very important religious aspect to Cantor's struggle to deal with the infinite
무한의 문제를 다루었던
그의 투쟁에는
and face the problems of not being able to resolve
중요한 종교적 측면이 있습니다
many of the open questions that he himself raised for the first time.
1884년까지 칸토어는 2년 이상
연속체 가설과 씨름했습니다
By 1884, Cantor has been working solidly on the continuum hypothesis for over 2 years.
그에 대한 인격적, 학문적인 공격은
날로 심해지고 있었죠
At the same time the personal and professional attacks on him have become more and more extreme.
버틸수 있을지 자신이 없다고
친구에게 털어놓기도 했습니다
In fact he writes to a friend saying he's not sure he can take them any more.
결국, 버티지 못했습니다
And indeed he can't.
그해 5월경 그는 심각한
신경쇠약에 걸렸습니다
By May of that year, he has a massive nervous breakdown.
성격이 뒤바뀔 정도로 심했는데,
그의 딸이 말하길
His daughter describes how his whole personality is transformed.
사납게 고함을 치다가도 갑자기
극단적으로 조용해지곤 했답니다
He would rant and rave and then fall completely and uncommunicatively silent.
결국 이곳 할레의 정신병원
네르펜클리닉에 입원했습니다
Eventually he is brought here to the Nervenklinik in Halle which is an asylum.
프랭크 필먼 - 정신과 의사, 할레 대학병원
요즘 말로 하면
그는 조울증이었습니다
Today we'd call it, Cantor suffered from manic depressive illness.
칸토어를 맡았던 의사들 대부분의
진료 기록이 남아 있는데
From Cantor's time we're left the case notes of
most of his psychiatrists describe in the notes for example
정신이 나가서
소리를 지르기도 했고
we see that he at times was quite disturbed, screaming,
심각한 조증 발작으로
매우 힘들어 했습니다
and see that he was really suffering from severe bouts of mania.
때로는 화를 내기도 하고
Sometimes he would be angry
과대 망상이나 피해 망상에
빠지기도 했습니다
and he would have ideas of grandeur, and sometimes he also had ideas of persecution.
신경쇠약에 걸린 후로
모든 것이 달라졌습니다
After his breakdown everything about Cantor is transformed.
친구에게 자신이 수학을 다시
할수있을지 잘 모르겠다고도 했고
He tells a friend he's not sure he'll ever be able to do mathematics again.
수학 강의를 그만두고 철학을 강의하면
안될지 대학에 문의하기도 했습니다
He asks the university if he can stop teaching math and teach philosophy instead.
그러나, 수학을 포기해야 할지
회의하던 이 와중에도
But interestingly during this whole time,
despite having claimed he'll not be able to do mathematics again,
연속체 가설에 대한 연구는
그만둔 적이 없었습니다
he never stops working on the continuum hypothesis.
도저히 이 문제를
내려놓을수 없었나 봅니다
It's as if he just can't put it down. Can't look away.
증명을 찾아내야겠다,
이런 생각밖에 안 듭니다
You can only think, 'I must find a proof.'
카린 리히터 - 수학자, 할레 대학
저도 이해가 가는데..
수학자는 24시간 내내 수학자니까요
This I can understand, because when you are a mathematician
then you are for all the time a mathematician.
수학은 삶의 일부입니다
It's a form of living for you.
종일 수학에 대해 생각하게 되고,
이 생각에서 떠나기는 어렵습니다
You must think about mathematics and you can't think anything else the whole day.
계속 생각에 생각을 거듭하며
You are thinking and thinking and thinking
'답을 찾아야 돼..'
and you say 'I must find it.'
계속 거기에 몰두하게 되죠
I must, I must, I must.. you can't think of anything else.
1884년 8월,
그의 연구를 누구보다 지지했던
In August of 1884 he writes a letter to his friend and colleague,
친구이자 동료인 미타그-레플러에게
보낸 편지는 흥분에 차 있습니다
the last man who still publishes his work, a man called Mittag-Leffler.
And the letter is ecstatic.
여기서 그는 "마침내 해냈습니다.
연속체 가설이 참임을 증명했습니다."
He says, "I've done it. I've proved the continuum hypothesis, it's true."
그러면서 조만간
증명을 보내겠다고 적었습니다
And he promises that he'll send the proof in the following weeks.
그러나 감감무소식이었죠
But the proof never comes.
그리고 3개월 후
두번째 편지에는
Instead, three months later the second letter arrives.
칸토어의 당혹감이
여실히 드러납니다
And in this one, you can feel Cantor's embarrassment.
"미안합니다, 증명했다는
주장을 하지 말았어야 하는데.."
He says, "I'm sorry, I should never have claimed that I'd proved it."
"나의 아름다운 증명은
모두 무너졌습니다."
He says, "My beautiful proof lies all in ruins."
그 무너진 잔해를
편지에서 볼 수 있습니다
And you can see the wreckage of his work in the letter.
그런데 그로부터 3주 뒤
But then three weeks after that
이 편지에서는
다른 주장을 합니다
this letter arrives and in it he says,
"연속체 가설이 거짓임을
증명했습니다."
"I've proved that the continuum hypothesis is not true."
이 패턴이 계속됩니다
And this pattern continues.
참이라고 증명했다가..
He proves that it is true,
또 거짓이라고 확신했다가..
오락가락합니다
and then he's convinced that it's not true. Back and forth.
그러면서 칸토어는
서서히 미쳐 갔습니다
And in fact what Cantor is doing is driving himself slowly insane.
초기 단계 증상 중의 하나는..
One of things that will happen, especially in the early stages,
또는 정신 분열 휴지기
이전 단계의 증상은..
and the stages just before a schizophrenic break, but also in the early stages,
환자가 주변 사물에
지나치게 집중하는 것입니다
would be that the patient is in a way looking too hard at the world in too concentrated a way.
말하자면 경직된 자세로
인식하는 것입니다
There's a kind of rigidity of the perceptual stance.
연속체 가설 앞에 좌절하면서,
그는 무한을 협곡에 비유했습니다
When he could not solve the continuum hypothesis, Cantor came to describe the infinite as an abyss,
그가 본 것과 그가 아는 것
사이에 있으나, 결코 닿을 수 없는..
a chasm perhaps.. between what he had seen and what he knew must be there,
but could never reach.
보통사람 같으면 별 의미가 없다고
흘려 버릴 사물에 대해서도
What can happen is that some object in the world that the rest of us would
거기에 뭔가 상징이 숨어 있다고
착각하는 것입니다
just consider as a sort of random thing there seems somehow symbolic in some way.
찾아야 돼, 찾아야 돼..
I must, I must, I must..
뭔가를 이해하려면 그것을
자세히 들여다봐야 하죠
There is a way in which in order to understand something you have to look very hard at it.
하지만, 한발 물러나 전체적인
맥락을 보는 능력 또한 필요합니다
But you also have to be able to sort of move away from it and kind of see it in a kind of context.
대상에만 지나치게 집중하는 사람은
이런 맥락을 놓치게 됩니다
And the person who stares too hard can often lose that sense of context.
칸토어는 완전히 회복되지 못했습니다
Cantor never fully recovered.
그는 풀지 못할 문제와 싸우며
여생을 보냈고
For the rest of his life, he would be drawn back to work on the problem he could not solve
좌절할 때마다
깊은 상처를 입었습니다
and each time it would hurt him profoundly.
1899년, 그는 다시 한번
연속체 가설을 붙들었고
1899, Cantor returned once again to work on the continuum hypothesis.
또다시 상태가 나빠져
정신병원으로 되돌아왔습니다
And again it made him ill, and he returned to the asylum.
그리고 다시 회복될 무렵
He was just recovering from this breakdown
아들 루돌프가 열세살 생일을
나흘 앞두고 갑자기 죽었습니다
when his son Rudolph died suddenly, four days short of his 13th birthday.
그는 친구에게 쓴 편지에서
Cantor wrote to a friend saying
아들이 자신으로부터 물려받은
음악적 재능을 언급했습니다
how his son had had a great musical talent, just as he had had when he was a boy.
칸토어는 수학을 하기 위해
음악을 포기했죠
But he had set music aside in order to go into mathematics.
루돌프 칸토어 1886-1899
아들이 죽자, 그는 이제
And now with the death of his son,
음악에 대한 자신의 꿈도
함께 죽었다고 느꼈습니다
he felt that his own dream of musical fulfillment had died with him.
아빠!
Papa!
칸토어는 자신이 왜 음악 대신
수학을 택했었는지조차
Cantor went on to say that he could no longer even remember why he himself
기억이 나지 않는다고
말하기도 했습니다
had left music in order to go into math.
그를 수학으로 불러들이고
삶과 연구에 의미를 부여했던..
That secret voice which had once called him on to mathematics
and given meaning to his life and work..
신이라고 믿었던 비밀의 목소리..
The voice he identified with God..
그 목소리마저 그를 버렸습니다
That voice too had left him.
칸토어의 이야기는
일단 여기까지입니다
Here we have to leave Georg Cantor.
시대적인 맥락을 무시하고
칸토어의 삶만 보면
Because, if we treat Cantor's story in isolation
단지 불운한 개인의 삶으로
생각될 수도 있습니다
it makes it into a tragic but obscure footnote to the broader sweep of history.
그러나, 칸토어가 판도라의 상자를
연 것이 아닐까 하는 불길함은
Whereas in fact, the fear that Cantor had dislodged something
돌처럼 단단해 보이던 것이
모래처럼 손에서 빠져나가는 듯한
was part of a much broader feeling that things once felt to be solid were slipping.
한층 더 넓은 범위의
불안감으로 이어집니다
같은 시기 루트비히 볼츠만의 이야기는
이 불안감을 더 잘 드러냅니다
A feeling seen more clearly in the story of his great contemporary,
a man called Ludwig Boltzmann.
칸토어가 수학에서 혁명적인
아이디어를 냈다가 배척당한 것처럼
Just as Cantor had revolutionary ideas in mathematics and was opposed
동시대의 볼츠만도 물리학에서
비슷한 일을 겪었습니다
so Boltzmann, his contemporary, had revolutionary ideas in physics and was equally opposed.
루트비히 볼츠만의 묘입니다
This is Ludwig Boltzmann's grave.
저것이 그를 죽인 방정식입니다
That, carved on it, is the equation which killed him.
(볼츠만 방정식)
칸토어처럼 볼츠만의 아이디어도
시기를 잘못 만난 탓이었습니다
And it did so because like Cantor, Boltzmann's ideas were out of step with his times.
칸토어가 영원하고 완벽한 논리라는
수학의 이상에 흠집을 냈다면
Cantor had undermined the ideal of a timeless and perfect logic in math.
볼츠만의 공식은 영원한 질서라는
물리학의 이상에 도전한 것입니다
Boltzmann's formula and his destiny was to undermine the ideal of a timeless order in physics.
이들은 수학, 물리를 넘어 확실성이라는
일반적인 개념을 허물었습니다
Together, their ideas were part of a general undermining of certainty
in the wider world outside of math and physics.
- 무질서의 천재 -
볼츠만과 칸토어의 시대는
과학, 철학 뿐만 아니라
Boltzmann's and Cantor's times craved certainty
정치, 예술 등에서도
확실성을 열망하던 때였습니다
in politics, in art as well as in science and philosophy.
겉보기에는 단단해 보이지만
알맹이는 흔들거리는 시대였습니다
They were times that looked on the surface solid and certain
but felt themselves to be teetering and sliding.
구식 질서는 점점 쇠퇴하고
곧 불행이 다가올 조짐이 보였습니다
The old order was dying and it was as if they could already feel disaster's gravitational pull.
카를 크라우스가 '종말의 실험실'*이라
불렀던 비엔나에서는
* 구시대와 현대가 교차하는 1900년 무렵
비엔나의 세기말적 분위기를 비유한 표현
In Vienna which was called by Karl Kraus 'laboratory for apocalypse'.
카를 지그문트 - 수학자, 비엔나 대학
합스부르크 제국의 몰락이
멀지 않았다는 관측이 있었습니다
There was this feeling that this political construct of The Habsburg Empire
couldn't last for much longer.
아주 기묘한 시대였습니다
They were very strange times.
한편에서는 권력층이 20년씩이나 걸려
오스트리아 제국의 기념 건물을 만들어
On the one hand, those in power spent 20 years building the monuments of Imperial Vienna,
현재의 질서가 영원하리라고
선언했습니다
to declare, that this order, firm on its foundations, would last forever.
부자는 언제나 성 안에..
The rich man would always be in his castle,
빈자는 언제나 성 밖에..
the poor man always at his gate.
그러나 사실 한편으로는
제국은 거의 망하기 직전이었습니다
But on the other hand, the empire was actually on its last legs.
당대 지식인층의 경향을
시인 호프만슈탈은 이렇게 요약했습니다
And the intellectual tenor of the times was summed up by the poet Hoffmanstahl,
구세대에서는 단단한 것으로
믿어왔던 것들이 사실은..
who said that what previous generations believed to be firm was in fact, what he called
그의 표현을 빌면 'das Gleitende'
'das Gleitende'
즉 '미끄러져 빠져나간다'는 것입니다
- the slipping or sliding away of the world.
그 표현이 비엔나.. 그리고 다른 곳들의
시대적 분위기를 말해준다고 생각합니다
I think that describes the feeling in Vienna.. in other places too,
아직 무너지진 않았지만
곧 그렇게 될 것처럼 보이는
but particularly in Vienna, in this capital of an empire that hadn't crumbled yet.
제국의 수도인 비엔나 분위기를
특히 잘 묘사한 문구 같습니다
But it looked like that too.. break-down.. this characterizes it very well.
볼츠만 시대의 과학적 의문들은
이러한 배경에 반하는 것이었습니다
And it was against this background that the scientific questions of Boltzmann's times were understood.
비엔나 대학의 안마당입니다
This is the great courtyard of the University of Vienna.
이곳을 거친 유명한 학자들의 흉상들
사이에 볼츠만의 것도 있습니다
And these are the busts of all of the greats who've ever taught here.
Boltzmann's here too.
그러나 이 많은 사람들 중
동시대인 상당수가
But many of his contemporaries men, more influential in their day even than he was,
입을 모아 볼츠만의 이론에
반대했습니다
lined up to oppose him and his ideas.
그것은 과학적인 측면만큼이나
이념적인 반대였습니다
But their opposition was as much ideological as it was scientific.
그때까지의 물리학은 확실성과
질서가 뚜렷한 세계관이었습니다
The physics of Boltzmann's time was still the physics of certainty, of an ordered universe
신이 내린 영구적이며 예측 가능한
법칙에 의해 결정되는 질서이죠
determined from above by predictable and timeless God given laws.
볼츠만은, 질서는
신이 부여한 것이 아니라
Boltzmann suggested that the order of the world was not imposed from above by God
원자들의 무작위적인 충돌로부터
비롯되는 것이라고 제안했습니다
but emerged from below from the random bumping of atoms.
당시에는 급진적인 생각이었지만
지금은 우리의 세계관의 기초이죠
A radical idea, at odd with his times, but the foundation of ours.
볼츠만이 삶을 마감한 곳에서 멀지 않은
아드리아 해안의 트리에스테에서
Professor Mussardo lives and works in Trieste on the Adriatic coast
거주하며 일하고 있는
무사르도 교수를 만났습니다
not far from where Boltzmann's life ended.
볼츠만에 관한 전문가이며,
같은 분야를 연구하고 있습니다
He is an expert on Boltzmann and works on the same kind of physics.
그가 독일 물리학자들에게
충분히 인정받지 못한
I think that there were two reasons why he could not get fully accepted
쥬세페 무사르도 - 물리학자, 트리에스테 국제고등과학원
두가지 이유가
있었다고 생각합니다
and recognized by the German physicists.
우선, 그의 이론은 눈에 보이지 않는
원자에 기반한 것입니다
One of them was that he was based all his theory on atom that people cannot see.
당대 가장 영향력 있는
과학철학자였던 에른스트 마흐가
And this was the reason of the very very strong criticism by Ernst Mach,
극렬히 비판했던 것도
이 점이었습니다
one of the most influential philosopher of science at that time.
마흐의 비판은 이겁니다:
So the critic of Mach was simply:
"볼 수도 없고 필요도 없는 원자를 왜
가정하고, 논의에 포함시켜야 하는가?"
"Atom? I cannot see, I don't need it, they do not exist. So why we should bring them in the game?"
보이지 않는 원자의 존재를
주장하는 것도 모자라서
Worse than insisting on the reality of something people could not see,
행동을 예측하기 어려운 원자를
물리학의 근본으로 삼는다는 것은
to base physics on atoms meant to base it on things whose behaviour was too complex to predict,
확실성보다는 확률에 기반한
전혀 새로운 종류의 물리학을 뜻합니다
which meant an entirely new kind of physics - one based on probabilities, not certainties.
두번째 이유는..
이것도 혁명적인 생각인데
Then there was a second aspect. It was revolutionary as well.
물리학에 확률을 도입하고, 나아가
확률의 역할을 강조했다는 것입니다
And this consists in putting and emphasizing the role of probability in the physics world.
사람들은 딱 부러지는
물리 법칙에 익숙해져 있었죠
And people were used to law of physics or science as exact,
영구 불변이며 불확실함 따위는
허용하지 않는 법칙 말입니다
once established they stay there forever, there is no room for uncertains.
그가 무대에 올려놓은 두가지,
즉 눈에 보이지 않는 '원자'..
So there introducing into the game two ingredients like atom invisible,
그리고 '확률', 즉 확실성 대신
가능성의 예측만 허용한다는 관점..
and probability, namely the fact that it's not certain,
you can predict probably what's going on but not certainly..
이것들은 당시 과학적 세계관과
크게 상반되는 것이었습니다
well this really contrasted very very much with the scientific spirit of the time.
그래서 문제가 생겼죠
And therefore this produced a trouble.
볼츠만의 천재성은
확률을 기꺼이 수용했다는 것입니다
Boltzmann's genius was that he could accept probability.
기존의 기계론적인 물리학으로는
결코 이해할 수 없었던
This meant he could begin to understand complex phenomena like fire and water and life,
불, 물, 생명 같은 복잡한 현상들을
이해하는 단초를 얻은 것입니다
things which traditional physics - the physics of mechanics - never could.
그러나 그 이론은 확률에 의존하므로
확실성을 훼손하는 것으로 여겨져
But because his solution relied on probability, and probability undermines certainty,
아무도 귀기울이지 않았습니다
no one wanted to hear him.
그 또한 칸토어와 마찬가지로
무자비한 반대에 부딪쳤고
And so just like Cantor, he faced implacable opposition
무척 힘들어 했습니다
which he too found extremely difficult to deal with.
볼츠만은 때와 장소를
잘못 만난 것 같군요
It seems like Boltzmann was just the wrong man in the wrong place..
물론, 물론입니다, 맞아요..
Absolute. Absolute. It's true..
20년만 뒤에 들고 나왔더라도..
If he'd just had his idea 20 years later..
더 늦게, 그리고 잉글랜드였다면
당대 최고 물리학자 대접을 받았을걸요
Later and in England, he'd have been the most successful physicist of that time. It's true.
만나는 이들마다 적이었다고나 할까요,
에른스트 마흐와도 무척 자주 마주쳤는데..
Somehow he met all his enemies. So he met Ernst Mach often.. they even crossed in a very..
- 사방이 적이고, 아군은 없고..
- 아군은 없고, 맞아요
- All his enemies but none of his friends.
- Not his friends, it's true.
볼츠만의 생각이 당시의 관념에 비추어
급진적이었다는 것은 쉽게 알 수 있습니다
It is not hard to see how Boltzmann's ideas were so radically at odds with his times.
과학이 아닌 사회적 관점에서
특히 그렇죠
Especially when applied not just to physics but to the social world.
전통적인 과학에는 신이 창조한 세계라는
관점이 깃들어 있습니다
Classical science, classical physics, gives you this image of a God ordered creation,
완벽하고 영원한 법칙들에 의해
반석 위에 놓여진 삼라만상의 세계..
where everything is set in stone according to perfect and eternal rules,
만물은 저마다 정해진 제자리가 있고
예측 가능하게 움직인다는 시각입니다
everything is predictable, everything has its place, and everything is in its place.
이곳 비엔나 중앙 묘지야말로
어찌보면 그 이상적인 표본입니다
But when you come here to the Central Cemetery of Vienna,
you see the idealized vision of that idea.
모든 것이 예측 가능하고,
모든 이가 정해진 자리를 차지하고 있죠
Because here everything is predictable.
Everybody does have a place and everybody is in their place.
그러나 이런 확실성이
정치적으로는 바람직할지라도
But the problem is, while such certainty might seem desirable politically,
생명이 살아숨쉬는, 열역학이 지배하는,
진짜 세상은 이런 모습이 아닙니다
the real world, the living world, the world described by thermodynamics just isn't like that.
완벽하고 영원한 세상은
변화가 없는 죽은 세상입니다
A timeless and perfect world never changes, but it is dead.
열역학의 세상, 진짜 세상은
끊임없는 변화에 의해 유지됩니다
The real world, the thermodynamic world is alive precisely because it is full of change.
물론, 변화는 생명을 부여하지만
무질서와 쇠퇴도 함께 가져다줍니다
But of course that life-giving change also brings with it disorder and decay.
로저 펜로즈 - 수학자, 옥스포드 대학
그런데 문제가 생깁니다. 뉴턴 역학은
시간에 대해 대칭적, 가역적이죠
But then the problem arises. If you then say, well
Newtonian mechanics on which you're depending is reversible in time.
그렇다면, 시간에 대해
대칭적인 기본 원리들로부터
So how can you derive a law which is asymmetrical in time
시간에 대해 비대칭적인 법칙이
어떻게 생겨날 수 있을까요?
from basic principles which are symmetrical in time.
시간의 방향을 거꾸로 돌려도
뉴턴 물리학은 아무 문제가 없습니다
You run a clock backwards, it's just as good Newtonian physics as if you run it forwards.
그런데도 엔트로피는
'미래'로 갈수록 증가한단 말이죠
Yet the entropy increases in the future.
무질서와 쇠퇴가
얼마나 축적되었는가,
But it is precisely this accumulation of disorder and decay
이것이 바로 볼츠만이 엔트로피를
이해한 방식입니다
that science calls entropy which Boltzmann had understood.
그 자체가 시간의 화살입니다
In short this is really the arrow of time.
사물이 점점 무질서해지는 방향이
시간의 화살의 방향이죠
You can measure the arrow of time just seeing how things become more and more disordered.
자연의 근본적인 경향성이며, 볼츠만은
이것을 정확하게 정량화했습니다
(묘비에 적혀 있던 볼츠만 방정식)
So it's a natural tendency in the world that Boltzmann quantified precisely.
저는 그를 '무질서의 천재'라고 부릅니다
Indeed I call him the 'genius of disorder'.
엔트로피에 관한 볼츠만의 연구는
Boltzmann's work on entropy showed why
모든 계가 완벽함을 잃고
무질서해지는 이유를 설명합니다
no system can be perfect, why there must always be some disorder.
물리학에서 말하는 시간 개념도
새로이 정립했습니다
It also revolutionized the idea of time in physics.
고전 물리학에서는 시간과 모든것이
앞으로든 뒤로든 흐를 수 있습니다
In classical physics, everything including time can run equally well forwards as backwards.
그러나 열역학에서는, 적어도 시간만큼은
앞으로만 흐를 수 있습니다
Yet in thermodynamics, while everything else is reversible,
time moves inexorably forward like an arrow.
엔트로피 개념은 철학적, 정치적으로도
중요한 영향을 끼쳤습니다
The idea of entropy had a profound philosophical and political significance.
엔트로피는 결국 시간의 흐름은
만물의 쇠퇴로 이어짐을 의미합니다
Entropy is what changes the ticking of a clock into the destroyer of all things.
젊음에서 노년으로 변해가는
거역할 수 없는 흐름의 원리입니다
It is what underlies the inexorable passage from youth to old age.
쇠퇴를 의미하는 엔트로피 앞에서는
그 무엇도 영원할 수 없습니다
Entropy is decay, and with decay nothing lasts forever.
볼츠만의 방정식은
숙명적인 유한함을 의미합니다
Boltzmann had in essence captured mortality in an equation.
물리학은 이제 신이 부여한 질서조차
영원할 수 없음을 선언했습니다
Physics now declared that no order, not even a God given one would last forever.
신이 못박아 놓은 자연의 질서란
존재하지 않는다는 통찰은
That there was no natural order that God had set in stone
볼츠만이 가장 존경했던 한 과학자가
이미 지적한 바 있습니다
had already been pointed out by the scientist Boltzmann most admired
찰스 다윈입니다
Charles Darwin.
영원한 완전무결함이 사라진 자리는
진화와 멸종의 파도가 대신합니다
In place of timeless perfection was a dance of evolution and extinction.
이러한 끊임없는 변화라는 개념을
With his equation of entropy,
볼츠만은 엔트로피 방정식을 통해
물리학의 핵심 원리로 도입한 것입니다
Boltzmann brought this picture of constant change into the very heart of physics itself.
볼츠만도 이러한 유사성을
거의 확실히 인지하고 있었습니다
Did Boltzmann understand the similarity?
Almost certainly.
자신의 세대가 어떻게 기억될것으로
생각하냐는 질문에 그는,
When Boltzmann was asked how his century would be remembered
물리학의 세기가 아닌
다윈의 세기로 기억될거라고 했습니다
he did not choose a physicist. He said it would be the century of Darwin.
볼츠만은 다윈의 학설에서
정적이지 않은 생명의 진화,
So he likes in Darwin the momentum, the evolution of life that is not static,
때로는 점프처럼 진행되는
진보라는 아이디어를 좋아했고
and the fact that there is progress, progress as sometimes this jump in it,
이전의 관념적 사고방식에
바탕을 둔 과학으로는
and the fact that he cannot address life aspect
생명 현상을 해석할 수 없다는
시각에 찬동했습니다
with ideas of science that before was kind of ideological ground.
볼츠만의 생각은 칸토어나 다윈
못지 않은 혁명적인 것이었습니다
Boltzmann's ideas, like Cantor's and Darwin's, were revolutionary
그 자신은 별로
의식하지 않았지만 말입니다
even though he did not think of them that way.
하지만 그가 살던 시기에는
But his times were frightened times..
새로운 생각이 사회의 구조를 무너뜨릴지
모른다는 두려움이 팽배해 있었습니다
times when people felt new ideas could upset society's fragile structure and bring it down.
19세기말 비엔나 사회는
정치, 철학, 예술, 과학 등
At the end of the 19th century, Viennese society was searching for some certainty, some principle,
어느 분야에서든 확실성과 원리를
추구하던 분위기였습니다
whether it was in politics, philosophy, the arts or science.
그러나, 모든 것을 통합하고
떠받칠 수 있는 철학적 토대는
But there didn't appear to be any philosophy capable of holding everyone together
결코 발견되지 않을듯 했습니다
upon which everything else could be based.
비엔나 대학은 철학을
찬양하는 뜻에서
So when the university commissioned Gustav Klimt
구스타프 클림트에게
천장 벽화를 부탁했는데
to paint the ceiling to celebrate philosophy
이것이 그 결과물입니다
this is what they got.
이것을 모욕이라고 느낀 스무명의 교수들이
벽화를 내리라고 청원하기도 했답니다
Such was the outrage that twenty professors petitioned to have the painting removed.
어찌됐든 확실성을 찬양하려는
노력은 실패한 셈입니다
Now whatever else it is, it's not a celebration of certainty.
이 시대의 급진주의자들은 확실성을 좇는
구식 질서가 허물어질것을 알았습니다
The radicals of Boltzmann's times knew the old order with its worn out certainties was doomed.
하지만 비엔나 사회는 새로움을
받아들일 준비가 되어 있지 않았고
But Viennese culture was not ready to embrace the new.
볼츠만은 갈 곳이 없었습니다
And Boltzmann was caught in the middle.
논쟁에 대처하는 방식에서도
그의 완고한 성격이 드러나는데
As a scientist his personality entered deeply into the game because he was very stubborn.
비판을 단순한 비판이 아니라
자신에 대한 공격으로 받아들였습니다
Not self ironic.. he could not take it criticism, he always take personally.
그는 열정에 찬 인물이었고
And Boltzmann was definitely a passion man.
아주 명랑했다가도
극도로 우울해지는 등
He used to swing rapidly from incredible joy to deep depression.
감정의 기복이 심했습니다
나이가 들고 논쟁에 지쳐가면서
As Boltzmann got older and more exhausted from the struggle,
조울증은 더 심해졌습니다
these mood swings became more and more severe.
자신의 이론을 납득시키느라
더 많은 에너지를 빼앗겼습니다
More and more of Boltzmann's energy was absorbed in trying to convince his opponents
that his theory was correct.
그는 "이 목표는 내 삶의 의미이며
모든것을 희생할 가치가 있다."고 했습니다
He wrote, "No sacrifice is too high for this goal which represents the whole meaning of my life."
볼츠만은 생애 마지막 10년동안
연구는 전혀 하지 않았습니다
Last year of Boltzmann he didn't do any research at all. I'm talking about the last 10 years.
그보다는 철학적 논쟁에 몰두하며
자신의 주장을 분명히 밝히고
He was fully immersed in a dispute, philosophical dispute, tried to make his point,
같은 개념을 되풀이하여 주장하는
저술 활동에 집중했습니다
writing books which were most of time the same repeating the same concept and so on.
앞으로 나아가지 못하는
쳇바퀴를 돌리고 있었던거죠
So you can see he was in a loop that didn't go ahead.